
<!-- $Id$ -->
<content>
  <chapter title="The epeios.cgi script">
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">The <raw>epeios.cgi</raw> is a script actually written in Perl, (but this woud probably change in the future), which is called by the http server. Its goal is to relay the http request to the CGID, and to transform the XML flow returned by the CGID to an HTML flow which is sent to the http server. To work properly, there are some keys wich must be defined in the user request, and it also needs a configuration file.</para>
    </section>
    <chapter title="The configuration file">
      <section>
        <para xml:space="preserve">The <raw>epeios.cgi</raw> script deduces the name of the configuration file from the value of the '_target' key in the http request. This configuration file contains the location of the CGID, and the path where the XSL file can be found.</para>
        <para xml:space="preserve">The location of the CGID must be put on the first line of the configuration file, in <raw>&lt;host>:&lt;service></raw> format. The second line must contain the path, without the tailing '/' of '\', where are the XSL files.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter title="The user request keys.">
      <section>
        <para xml:space="preserve">The value of the key '_target' defines which CGID is concerned by the request, more precisely which configuration file must be used (see previous chapter). The <raw>epeios.cgi</raw> script appends a '.conf' extension to the '_target' value, and this give the name of the configuration file. The configuration file must be in the same directory as the <raw>epeios.cgi</raw> script.</para>
        <para xml:space="preserve">The value of the '_skin' key gives which XSL file should be used to transform the XML flow returned by the CGID in a HTML file. The <raw>epeios.cgi</raw> script adds simply a '.xsl' extension to the value of the '_skin' key, and uses the file with this name located at the path given in the configuration file.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </chapter>
</content>