
<!-- $Id$ -->
<content>
  <chapter title="Name">
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>mll2html</raw> - reformats, in HTML, a text file containing mailing lists descriptions. 

</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Synopsis">
    <section>
      <para>
        <raw>mll2html [-c|--convert] [options] &lt;source_file> &lt;template-file> [dest-file]</raw>
      </para>
      <para>
        <raw>mll2html --version</raw>
      </para>
      <para>
        <raw>mll2html --license</raw>
      </para>
      <para>
        <raw>mll2html --help</raw>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Description">
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
The <raw>mll2html</raw> purpose is to reformat a text file, containing description of mailing-lists, in a more convenient HTML file. It was part of the job list for the <link URL="http://www.fsf.org/" type="external" aspect="long">FSF</link> WEB server, from which it was removed since the FSF use this software.</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>source-file</raw> is the text file containing the mailing-lists description. It has the following structure, which was deduced from a file provided by the FSF.</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">The first lines constitute the head section. They contains the title, date of update, authors, copyrights, etc. ...</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">With the first line beginning with a star (<raw>*</raw>) begins the general sections. They contain general information about the mailing lists. They are divided in items which each begins with a line beginning with a star. Stars and following spaces before the first character are ignored. This line contains the title of the item.</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">When there is more than one line beginning with a star, then come the mailing-list sections. They are also divided in items. Each item begins with lines beginning with one or more stars, eventually followed by spaces (both stars and spaces are ignored). This lines contain the name of the list, the address of the corresponding newsgroup, e-mails, URL's, ...</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>template-file</raw> is a file containing the structure of the output file, that is, it is simply copied to the output file, with following tag's replaced by the given values :</para>
      <para>
        <list>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$HEAD$</raw> : is replaced by the head section.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$GENERAL_TOC$</raw> : is replaced by the list of the titles from the general sections.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$LISTS_TOC$</raw> :is replaced by the list of titles from the mailing lists sections.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$GENERAL_BODY$</raw> : is replaced by the general sections.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$LISTS_BODY$</raw> : is replaced by the mailing lists sections.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$$</raw> : is replaced by a unique <raw>$</raw>.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$COPYRIGHT$</raw> : is replaced by the copyright of the software.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$UPDATE$</raw> : is replaced by the date and time when the output file is generated.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$NAME$</raw> : is replaced by the name of the author.
</item>
          <item xml:space="preserve">
            <raw>$_END_$</raw> : it's a special tag. What follows this tags is written as is in the output file. It isn't analyze to detect a tag.
</item>
        </list>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">For each FTP, HTTP and NEWS address (whatever respectively begins with <raw>ftp://</raw>, <raw>http://</raw> and <raw>news://</raw> ) in <raw>source-file</raw>, a hypertext link is generated pointing to the given address. A hypertext link is also generated for e-mail addresses (whatever contains a <raw>@</raw> followed by a <raw>.</raw>). Links are generated even after the <raw>$_END_$</raw> tag.</para>
      <para>A template file can contain one or more of this tags, and a tag can be put more that once.</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>dest-file</raw> is the output file, in HTML (if none given, then the standard output is used).

</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <para>Options can take following values :</para>
      <list>
        <item xml:space="preserve">
          <raw>-l</raw>, <raw>--lists-file FILE</raw> : <raw>FILE</raw> is the file name which contains the body of the mailing-list sections. If you generate the TOC from the mailing-lists in another file then the one which contains the body (i.e. <raw>$LISTS_TOC$</raw> and <raw>$LISTS_BODY$</raw> are in separate template file), give for <raw>FILE</raw> the name of the file where the body of the lists is. <raw>FILE</raw> will be used for the hypertext links in the TOC.
</item>
        <item xml:space="preserve">
  <raw>-g</raw>, <raw>--general-file FILE</raw> : same as before, but for the general sections (<raw>$GENERAL_TOC$</raw> and <raw>$GENERAL_BODY$</raw> tags).
</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>mll2html --version</raw> prints the version of the software. Because this software uses Epeios libraries, you see the version of the sources from the software itself, and the version of the sources of the used Epeios libraries.</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
<raw>mll2html --license</raw> prints the license of the software.</para>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>mll2html --help</raw> prints a help message about how to use the software.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Return values">
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <raw>mll2html</raw> returns following values upon completion :<list>
          <item>0 : completed successfully.</item>
          <item>other value : an error occurs.</item>
        </list></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Links">
    <section>
      <para xml:space="preserve">
        <list>
          <item><link URL="http://epeios.org/software/mll2html/" type="external" aspect="long"><raw>mll2html</raw> homepage</link>.</item>
          <item><link URL="http://epeios.org/" type="external" aspect="long">The Epeios project homepage</link>, on which libraries <raw>mll2html</raw> is based.</item>
        </list></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Reporting bugs">
    <para xml:space="preserve">Report bugs to <contact adress="csimon@webmails.com" type="long">Claude SIMON</contact>.</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Author">
    <para xml:space="preserve">
      <raw>mll2html</raw> was developed by <contact adress="csimon@webmails.com" type="long">Claude SIMON</contact>.</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Standard conformance">
    <para>
      <list>
        <item>
          <link URL="http://epeios.org/" type="external" aspect="long">Epeios</link>.</item>
        <item>
          <link URL="http://www.gnu.org/" type="external" aspect="long">GNU</link>.</item>
      </list>
    </para>
  </chapter>
</content>
